<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en_us"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en_us" /><updated>2023-02-13T09:38:50+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ARIES Science club</title><author><name>Sal</name></author><entry><title type="html">Active Galaxies: Most Powerful Objects in the Universe – An Overview</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/activegalaxies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Active Galaxies: Most Powerful Objects in the Universe – An Overview" /><published>2023-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Active-Galaxies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/activegalaxies/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post"> Active galaxies are highly luminous astrophysical sources in the universe powered by “supermassive black holes” via processes known 
            as “accretion”. They contain a highly bright, compact region at the galaxy’s center called “active galactic nuclei” (AGN). Their emission spreads 
            over a wide range of frequencies through radio to γ-rays. Both thermal and non-thermal radiations from different components of AGN contribute to 
            the total observed emission. They exhibit extreme variations ranging from all the time-scale from minutes to years across the electromagnetic band.
            These variations occur as flares or quiescent/low-activity states. Studying the cause for such physical properties of AGNs through multi-frequency 
            data using ground and space-based observatories has been found to be one of the most effective ways in the past. Despite such studies in various 
            wavebands, there are several questions for which answers are not fully understood. In this talk, the speaker will briefly introduce AGN and its 
            current understanding status, along with the scope of AGN research.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <p class="post">We present to you the second talk of our ARIES Science Club by Dr. Krishna Mohana. On our Earth, the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) generates 
        particles with energies in the Tera electron volts (TeV) range, which is a lot! However, there are some mysterious and powerful objects in our Universe
        where this energy is just child's play. They are called AGN (Active Galactic Nuclei).
    </p>

    <p class="post">An AGN is a small region at the center of some galaxies that is far brighter than can be explained by the stellar population alone. AGNs 
        emit radiation from radio waves to gamma rays across the entire electromagnetic spectrum. Carl Seyfert discovered this incredible phenomenon in 1943. 
        The galaxies which contain these AGNs were thus named Seyfert Galaxies.
    </p>

    <figure>
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/figure1.jpg" alt="Unified model of AGN">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1: Unified model of AGN</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p>The AGN structure has certain key components:
        <ul class="post">
            <li>The central engine (supermassive black hole mass ~10<sup>8</sup> - 10<sup>9</sup> M<sub>&#9737</sub>)</li>
            <li>Accretion disk</li>
            <li>Corona</li>
            <li>Broad line region</li>
            <li>Narrow line region</li>
            <li>Dusty torus</li>
            <li>Relativistic jets</li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <p class="post">Further, AGNs are classified in terms of the observer's viewing angle, the energy of the jets, and the width of the emission line. The 
        picture below depicts the various classifications:
    </p>

    <figure style="text-align: center;">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/figure2.jpg" alt="classifications of AGN">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2: Classifications of AGNs</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p class="post">Another interesting consequence of AGN jets is Superluminal motion, which occurs when an emission region moves at a velocity close to the 
        speed of light along a direction that forms a small angle with the observer's line of sight. The time interval between the emission of two successive 
        photons, as measured in the observer's frame, is reduced & the source appears to move faster than its actual velocity.
    </p>

    <p class="post">Interestingly, in 1959, a star-like object was discovered in radio band. An optical starlight source was observed in the same region with 
        unusual properties, such as emission lines. These were termed quasi-stellar radio sources (in short, Quasars) because the nature of these objects is 
        entirely unknown. It is hard to prepare a short and appropriate nomenclature for them so that their essential properties are obvious from their name.
        Quasars, also a type of AGN, are the most luminous objects in our Universe, powered by supermassive black holes which are a billion times more massive
        than our Sun.
    </p>

    <p class="post">We can detect AGNs through multi-messenger astronomy (gamma-rays through radio waves, jets) and polarization. Polarization observation of 
        AGN jets provides valuableinformation about their magnetic field. Due to the magnetic field's twisting, we can observe the frame-dragging effect of a 
        spinning black hole and the differential rotation of the accretion disk
    </p>

    <p class="post">A few ground and space observatories to detect the AGN mechanisms are: EGRET(Energetic Gamma Ray Experiment Telescope), FGST (Fermi 
        Gamma-ray Space Telescope), SWIFT, India's AstroSAT, our ARIES's very own DOT 3.6m (Devesthal Optical Telescope). 
    </p>

    <p class="post">Through studying AGN, we can enhance our understanding of the origin of jets, emission mechanism, accretion disk, supermassive blackhole, 
        extragalactic sources, and early Universe, and hence, test the general theory of relativity.
    </p>

    <p class="post">Some of the numerous open questions in this field?
        <ul class="post">
            <li>Where along the jet, do the high-energy and very high-energy y-ray emissions
                predominantly originate?
            </li>
            <li>Whether the high energy emission mechanism is leptonic, hadronic, or mixed?
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <figure>
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/figure3.png" alt="krishna explaining">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 3: Dr. Krishna explaining the radiative processes involved in the jet emissions</figcaption>
    </figure>

</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>krishna</name></author><category term="AGN" /><category term="Relativistic Jets" /><category term="Accretion Disk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Active galaxies are highly luminous astrophysical sources in the universe powered by “supermassive black holes” via processes known as “accretion”. They contain a highly bright, compact region at the galaxy’s center called “active galactic nuclei” (AGN). Their emission spreads over a wide range of frequencies through radio to γ-rays. Both thermal and non-thermal radiations from different components of AGN contribute to the total observed emission. They exhibit extreme variations ranging from all the time-scale from minutes to years across the electromagnetic band. These variations occur as flares or quiescent/low-activity states. Studying the cause for such physical properties of AGNs through multi-frequency data using ground and space-based observatories has been found to be one of the most effective ways in the past. Despite such studies in various wavebands, there are several questions for which answers are not fully understood. In this talk, the speaker will briefly introduce AGN and its current understanding status, along with the scope of AGN research.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Eyes on the Sky: Current and upcoming telescopes of this decade</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Eyes-on-the-sky/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eyes on the Sky: Current and upcoming telescopes of this decade" /><published>2023-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Eyes-on%20-the-sky</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Eyes-on-the-sky/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post">The multi-wavelength and multi-messenger information received from the cosmic objects serves as a laboratory for astronomers to 
            understand the universe. With technology progressing at a rapid rate, how can astronomy lag behind? Already, there are multiple telescopes with
            apertures of 10-meter class and networks of telescopes operating across the globe, along with many multi-wavelength telescopes orbiting the earth.
            Data obtained from these telescopes have revolutionezed our understanding in the recent past. As a natural progression, the era of next-generation 
            telescopes started with the JWST launch last year. With multiple exciting projects lined up this decade, we can expect to get many new results with
            better data and enhanced precision.
        </p>
        <hr>    
    </blockquote>

    <p class="post"> Welcome to the first talk organized by the ARIES Science Club! Vivek Kr. Jha presented the first talk. He is also the mentor of our ARIES
        Science Club (ASC).The talk started with a basic introduction to telescopes. There are various types of telescopes depending on the wavelength we want
        to observe and the resolution that can be achieved. For example, optical and Radio waves can be observed from ground-based telescopes, whereas the same
        is not feasible for infrared, UV, and X-ray wavebands. To tackle that, we send the telescopes to specific points in higher atmosphere or space. Also,
        we have telescopes of different sizes and arrangements with different resolutions and use cases. For example, radio observations need a very large 
        aperture of the telescope, which is very difficult to make with a single disc antenna. For that array of small antennas is installed in a large open 
        area.
    </p>

    <p class="post"> The talk started with a basic introduction to telescopes. There are various types of telescopes depending on the wavelength we want to
        observe and the resolution that can be achieved. For example, optical and Radio waves can be observed from ground-based telescopes, whereas the same 
        is not feasible for infrared, UV, and X-ray wavebands. To tackle that, we send the telescopes to specific points in higher atmosphere or space. Also, 
        we have telescopes of different sizes and arrangements with different resolutions and use cases. For example, radio observations need a very large 
        aperture of the telescope, which is very difficult to make with a single disc antenna. For that array of small antennas is installed in a large open 
        area.
    </p>

    <figure>
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-03-talk/image1.jpg" alt="various sizes of telescope">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1: Upocoming telescopes sizes</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <figure>
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-03-talk/image2.png" alt="size of telescopes">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2: Comparison of size of various telescopes</figcaption>
    </figure>
    
     <p class="post">The speaker takes everyone through the journey of the capabilities of different telescopes, mainly those with a size greater than 8 meters.
        To list a few:
        <ul class="post">
            <li><em>South African Large Telescope (SALT)</em>: This is the largest single optical telescope in the southern hemisphere. However, it has a major 
                drawback. It cannot be steered to change the angle of the telescope, hence limiting the observations to a relatively small ring of the sky.
            </li>
            <li><em>Very Large Telescope (VLT)</em>: With its set of four 8.2 meter telescopes, it is one of the most technologically advanced telescope 
                systems due to its ability to perform interferometry using its built-in MUSE equipment. In interferometry, we divide a wide field of view 
                (large fringe) into smaller slits and then record their interference fringes created by combining the light from multiple telescopes. For 
                example, our galaxy is quite wide apart and needs multiple slits to cover its boundaries.
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <p class="post">Next the speaker talks about Radio telescopes a little bit. Optical wavebands are limited, but Radio has a large bandpass. Also, radio 
        observations can be taken in the daytime, unlike optical. The most advanced telescope for Radio observation is <em>VLA</em> in US and <em>ALMA</em> in 
        Europe. ALMA is the costliest ground-based telescope to be built to date, with 66 radio antennas in operation. The <em>Five hundred meter Aperture 
        Spherical Telescope (FAST)</em> in Guizhou, China, is the world’s largest field-aperture telescope. It works in the radio band 70 MHz- 3.0 GHz. India 
        has its own telescopes for radio observation. The <em>Giant Meterwave Radio Telescope (GMRT)</em> in Pune is the largest radio telescope in India. The
        main goal of this telescope was to observe the 21 cm line of the neutral Hydrogen. The USPs of this telescope are the 153 and 325 MHz frequencies, 
        which are critical in Radio astronomy.
    </p> 

    <p class="post">Other than optical and Radio telescopes, we also have UV and X-ray telescopes in space. The most popular globally is the 32 years old 
        <em>Hubble Space Telescope (HST)</em>, which has made fundamental contributions to the field. India’s <em>AstroSat</em>, launched in 2015, can also 
        detect X-ray polarization, a unique attribute of this telescope. Now, modern-day astronomy is progressing from multi-wavelength to multi-messenger 
        observation. By multi-messenger observation, it is implied that we are also looking for messengers other than photons, like neutrinos, cosmic rays, 
        and gravitational waves.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        A few take-home points from this lecture:
        <ul class="post">
            <li>Telescopes have increased in size over time, and the trend will continue in the coming future.</li>
            <li>A vast number of telescopes are coming up both on Earth and in space.</li>
            <li>They continue to expand our knowledge further, probing the Universe closer and closer to the Big Bang.</li>
            <li>Multi-messenger astronomy is the new norm, as has been with GW detection recently.</li>
            <li>India is part of a handful of major projects like SKA, TMT, and GMRT, with a possibility of a 10-meter class telescope in the future.</li>
        </ul> 
    </p>

</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>vivek</name></author><category term="Telescopes" /><category term="Multi-Messenger Information" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The multi-wavelength and multi-messenger information received from the cosmic objects serves as a laboratory for astronomers to understand the universe. With technology progressing at a rapid rate, how can astronomy lag behind? Already, there are multiple telescopes with apertures of 10-meter class and networks of telescopes operating across the globe, along with many multi-wavelength telescopes orbiting the earth. Data obtained from these telescopes have revolutionezed our understanding in the recent past. As a natural progression, the era of next-generation telescopes started with the JWST launch last year. With multiple exciting projects lined up this decade, we can expect to get many new results with better data and enhanced precision.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-03-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-03-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>