<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en_us"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en_us" /><updated>2023-06-19T06:48:27+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ARIES Science club</title><author><name>Sal</name></author><entry><title type="html">Transit Spectroscopy - A Tool to Probe the Exoplanet Atmosphere</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Transit-spectroscopy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transit Spectroscopy - A Tool to Probe the Exoplanet Atmosphere" /><published>2023-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Transit-spectroscopy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Transit-spectroscopy/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post">
            The transit method has proven immensely valuable in detecting exoplanets but also holds great potential for characterizing their atmospheres. In 
            this discussion, I will explore the utilization of both low and high-resolution transit spectroscopic techniques, which are employed to examine the 
            atmospheres of exoplanets using ground-based facilities such as HCT/HFOSC, Gemini/GMOS, Keck/HIRES, VLT/ESPRESSO, HARPS, etc.
        </p>
    </blockquote>

    <h5>
        What is Transit Method:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        The transit method is a popular method to detect and analyse the characteristics of many astronomical objects, like binary stars, exoplanets. Suppose 
        a far-away star has few planets. We can detect the variation of photon flux coming from the star with time using telescope detectors. It is called a 
        light curve. Now, when the planets of the star come in front of the star, in our FOV, the amount of flux coming from the star decreases, and therefore 
        the existence of the planets can be assumed from the light curve. The size of the orbit of the planets can be calculated from the time it takes to 
        orbit the star once, and the size of the planets can be obtained by noting the amount of dimming it has done in the light curve.
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-06-02-talk/figure1.gif" alt="light-curve-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1 : Dip in the light curve as a planet passes in front of a star <em>(Credit: University of Hertfordshire)</em>
        </figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>    
        Transit Spectroscopy:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        We can learn about the atmosphere of the exoplanet during transit. As the planet's atmosphere reabsorbs and scatters the photons coming from the star, 
        the transit depth (The amount of intensity dimming in the light curve of the star due to the planet) is wavelength dependent. In the UV and bluer part 
        of the optical the lines transit depth decreases with increasing wavelength due to Rayleigh scattering, whereas Na and K lines are visible in the 
        optical band and H<sub>2</sub>O and other molecular lines are visible in the NIR band.
    </p>

    <h5>
        Low-Resolution Spectroscopy:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>A reference star of the same spectral type as the host star is chosen in the same science frame.</li>
            <li> Low-resolution spectroscopic observations are taken continuously covering transit and out of transit.</li>
            <li>The fluxes of the host star at each wavelength are normalised by dividing it by the fluxes of reference star.</li>
            <li>The cumulative relative flux of the host star in each wavelength bin is then plotted as a function of phase to obtain the wavelength dependent transit 
                depth.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <h5>
        Merits and Demerits of LR Spectroscopy:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>It is useful for initial study of exoplanets and for understanding possible atmospheric signatures.</li>
            <li>Smaller telescopes (e.g, 2 m) are also capable of doing it.</li>
            <li>Number of data points is less.</li>
            <li>Observation alone cannot provide a detailed information about the atmosphere of the exoplanet.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <h5>
        High-Resolution Spectroscopy:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>High-resolution spectroscopic observations are taken continuously covering transit and out of transit.</li>
            <li>Stability of the wavelength solution throughout the observation is important.</li>
            <li>High Resolution Spectra is analysed to study individual spectral features of the exoplanet atmosphere.</li>
            <li>Residual planetary signal is obtained by subtracting individual in-transit spectra with master out of transit spectra.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <figure class="image", float="left">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-06-02-talk/figure2.png" alt="LR-spectra-image", style="width: 20rem;">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-06-02-talk/figure3.png" alt="HR-spectra-image", style="width: 20rem;">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2 : Low Resolution (R ~ 1200)(on the left) and High Resolution Spectra (R~65k)s (on the right)
        </figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>
        Merits and Demerits of HR Spectroscopy:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>Useful in studying the atmosphere of the exoplanets in more detail.</li>
            <li>Require more stabilised bigger telescopes.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-06-02-talk/figure4.png" alt="transit-light-curve-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 3 : During a transit along with an overall flux drop, there is an extra absorption happening in an absorption 
            feature <em>(Credit: ESO workshop 2022).</em>Examples of He (1083 nm) detection in the atmosphere of WASP-69b using CARMENES (Lisa Nortmann et al. 2018) and Li (671 nm) detection in the atmosphere of   WASP-76b (H. M. Tabernero et al 2021) using VLT/ESPRESSO.
        </figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>
        Main Steps to be followed:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>Telluric Correction</li>
            <li>Normalisation</li>
            <li>Spectra to the stellar rest frame</li>
            <li>Remove stellar contribution</li>
            <li>Shift the residual spectra to the planet rest frame</li>
            <li>Combine all the residual spectra</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <figure class="image", float="left">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-06-02-talk/figure5.png" alt="WASP69b-spectra-image", style="width: 20rem;">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-06-02-talk/figure6.jpg" alt="WASP76b-spectra-image", style="width: 20rem;">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 4 : Examples of He (1083 nm) detection in the atmosphere of WASP-69b using CARMENES (Lisa Nortmann et al. 2018) 
            and Li (671 nm) detection in the atmosphere of WASP-76b (H. M. Tabernero et al 2021) using VLT/ESPRESSO.
        </figcaption>
    </figure>
</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>athira</name></author><category term="Exoplanets" /><category term="Spectroscopy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The transit method has proven immensely valuable in detecting exoplanets but also holds great potential for characterizing their atmospheres. In this discussion, I will explore the utilization of both low and high-resolution transit spectroscopic techniques, which are employed to examine the atmospheres of exoplanets using ground-based facilities such as HCT/HFOSC, Gemini/GMOS, Keck/HIRES, VLT/ESPRESSO, HARPS, etc.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-06-02-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-06-02-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Coronal Holes and their Detection: A Simple Overview</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Coronal-holes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coronal Holes and their Detection: A Simple Overview" /><published>2023-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Coronal-holes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Coronal-holes/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post">
            Coronal Holes are the darkest and least active regions in the solar corona as observed on the solar disk and above the solar limb. They are 
            associated with high-speed solar winds that are responsible for a fraction of geomagnetic storms on Earth. Thus naturally its detection is crucial 
            for predicting space weather. We will take a look at some popular detection methods and how Neural Networks can help us take the field forward.
        </p>
    </blockquote>

    <h5>
        What are Coronal Holes?
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        Coronal Holes are regions in the solar Corona where the plasma is cooler and denser than the other parts. Coronal holes appear as dark areas in the 
        solar Corona in extreme ultraviolet (EUV) and soft X-ray solar images. They appear dark because they are cooler, less dense regions than the 
        surrounding plasma and are regions of open (locally), unipolar magnetic fields.
    </p>

    <figure class="image", float="left">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-05-26-talk/figure1.png" alt="magnetic-structures-image", style="width: 12rem;">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-05-26-talk/figure2.jpg" alt="coronal-holes-image", style="width: 12rem;">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1 : Schematic of different magnetic structures  of Sun (Left), Image of coronal holes taken from AIA observations 
            (Right)
        </figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption"><em>Source: Zhang, J., Temmer, M., Gopalswamy, N. et al. Earth-affecting solar transients: a review of progresses in 
            solar cycle 24. Prog Earth Planet Sci 8, 56 (2021). and  <a href="https://www.universetoday.com/82576/holes-in-the-suns-corona-in-2-d-3-d-and-
            video/">https://www.universetoday.com/82576/holes-in-the-suns-corona-in-2-d-3-d-and-video/</a></em> </figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>
        Signatures of Coronal Holes
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>If observed in EUV or Soft X-ray, the coronal holes appear as dark regions (darker than the surroundings).</li>
            <li>The magnetograms will appear to be predominantly unipolar since the magnetic field lines appear to be open locally.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <h5>
        Importance of Coronal Holes
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>Coronal Holes are associated with open magnetic field lines that extend into the heliosphere. Thus, the ions and electrons are accelerated 
                through these lines creating high-speed winds, which are responsible for a fraction of geomagnetic storms on Earth.</li>
            <li>The boundaries of Coronal Holes might play a role in the origin of slow solar winds.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <h5>
        A brief overview of a few existing methods
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>
                <h5>Simple Intensity Thresholding</h5>
                <p>A Histogram based method that uses intensity threshold and removes filaments using magnetograms. A single peak is observed in the absence 
                    of Coronal Holes, however, a double peak emerges in the Intensity histogram in the presence of coronal holes.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <h5>CHIMERA (Coronal Hole identification via multi-thermal emission recognition algorithm)</h5>
                <p>It analyses intensities in three bands (171 Å, 193 Å, and 211 Å) to segment pixels with similar properties together to a Coronal Hole. 
                    Coronal Holes have a typical temperature of 0.7 MK, which means they should produce peak emission in the 171 Å passband.</p>
            </li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <h5>
        Problems encountered while detecting Coronal Holes
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>Other features in the solar Corona, like filaments, Coronal dimming, etc., appear equally dark as Corona Holes.</li>
            <li>Due to the near-limb projection effects, the intensity-based segmentation techniques will perform worse as we go polewards. Also, brighter 
                structures will obscure the Coronal Holes as we move towards the pole.</li>
            <li>The shape, size, and location of Coronal Holes change over a few solar rotations and between solar maxima and solar minima.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <figure class="image", float="left">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-05-26-talk/figure3.png" alt="coronal-holes-image", style="width: 10rem;">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-05-26-talk/figure4.png" alt="coronal-holes-image", style="width: 10rem;">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2 : Coronal holes during Solar Maxima (Left) and Solar Minima (Right)</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption"><em>Source: <a href="https://svs.gsfc.nasa.gov/4854">https://svs.gsfc.nasa.gov/4854</a></em> </figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>
        Tackling these problems using Neural Networks
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ol class="post">
            <li>Neural Networks are known to have better accuracy.</li>
            <li>There is less human intervention.</li>
            <li>The network can pick out large time-scale patterns.</li>
            <li>They are usually faster.</li>
            <li>We have a large dataset at hand.</li>
        </ol>
        We can also create catalogues for CMEs and Solar Winds using these ML techniques, which will help future researchers.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        <em>Devesh’s future work will revolve around using various ML techniques to identify Coronal Holes.</em>
    </p>
</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>devesh</name></author><category term="Coronal holes" /><category term="Neural Network" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Coronal Holes are the darkest and least active regions in the solar corona as observed on the solar disk and above the solar limb. They are associated with high-speed solar winds that are responsible for a fraction of geomagnetic storms on Earth. Thus naturally its detection is crucial for predicting space weather. We will take a look at some popular detection methods and how Neural Networks can help us take the field forward.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-05-26-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-05-26-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Observational aspects of Coronal Heating in the context of kink oscillations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Observational-aspects-of-Coronal-Heating/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Observational aspects of Coronal Heating in the context of kink oscillations" /><published>2023-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Observational-aspects-of-Coronal-Heating</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Observational-aspects-of-Coronal-Heating/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post">
            Coronal heating is a problem that has puzzled scientists for decades. One proposed mechanism for coronal heating is the energy transfer in the 
            solar corona by Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) waves. Several types of MHD waves can be observed in the solar corona, and kink oscillations are a 
            ubiquitous manifestation of largely transverse MHD waves in the solar corona. In this talk, I'll touch upon the historical and introductory 
            aspects of coronal heating, shedding light on the observational perspective. Furthermore, we'll explore the intriguing topic of kink oscillations 
            and their related heating phenomena within the context of the most recent and cutting-edge imaging instruments.
        </p>
    </blockquote>

    <h5>
        What is the Solar Corona?
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        The Sun is surrounded by an atmosphere of gasses, and the Corona is the outermost layer. The Corona has a temperature of 3-4 orders of magnitude 
        greater than the visible surface (greater than a million degrees). Due to the relative brightness of the Sun's surface, it is only visible from Earth 
        during total solar eclipses.
    </p>

    <figure class="image", float="left">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-04-08-talk/figure1.jpg" alt="solar-eclipse-image", style="width: 12rem;">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-04-08-talk/figure2.jpg" alt="layers-of-sun-image", style="width: 12rem;">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1 : Illustration of the Corona observed during the Solar Eclipse (Left), and Schematic of the different layers 
            of the Sun (Right)</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption"><em>Source: <a href="www.timeanddate.com/eclipse/total-solar-eclipse.html">www.timeanddate.com/eclipse/total-solar-eclipse.html</a>
            and <a href="www.thesuntoday.org/solar-facts/powering-the-sun">www.thesuntoday.org/solar-facts/powering-the-sun</a> </em> </figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>
        What is the problem of Coronal heating?
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <em>"For decades, the problem has been known as the coronal heating problem, but it is now clear that coronal heating cannot be treated or explained 
            in isolation and that the heating of the whole solar atmosphere must be studied as a highly coupled system. The magnetic field of the Sun is known 
            to play a key role....</em>
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        <em>....the question of which mechanism or mechanisms are the dominant supplier of energy to the chromosphere and Corona is still open."</em>
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        <em>- (Parnell & De Moortel, 2012)</em>
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        In the 1890s, the solar surface temperature was derived to be around 6600K, using the newly-discovered Stefan-Boltzmann law. The solar photosphere 
        radiates like a blackbody; its spectrum gives T, and dark "Fraunhofer lines" reveal its chemical composition. However, during the 1870s total solar 
        eclipse revealed a complex outer solar corona. Spectrographs revealed unknown bright lines along with Fraunhofer lines.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        A strange emission line was observed in the green part of the spectrum. This emission line was thought to be due to a new and unknown element, and it 
        was named Coronium. Later scientists found that there is no new element and emission is coming from highly ionized atoms. Similarly, other unknown lines were identified as CaXII, FeIX, to FeXII. However, to ionise these elements to such a great extent 
        requires a very high temperature. Hence, it was calculated that the Corona must have temperatures greater than 1 million K. And so the coronal heating 
        problem began.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        What was strange was that, as we go higher up in the solar atmosphere, the temperature should decrease since plasma density decreases drastically. 
        However, it was not the case.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        Solar physicists have proposed two probable mechanisms for coronal heating.
        <ol class="post">
            <li><strong>Nano-Flare heating:</strong> In this theory, the Corona is heated by very small flares(nano-flares) being the energy source, which 
                could be detected through conventional telescopes.</li>
            <li><strong>Wave-Heating:</strong> In this theory, a countless number of magnetic field lines extending from the surface of the Sun are oscillated 
                by the dynamics of the convection on the solar surface, which delivers the energy to the Corona. The energy is then converted into heat in the 
                Corona.</li>
        </ol>
        Which of these is most important for chromospheric and coronal heating is still very much an open question.
    </p>

    <h5>
        Kink oscillations of coronal loops
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        Kink oscillations are the transverse displacement of the loop axis.
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-04-08-talk/figure3.png" alt="kink-oscillation-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2 : Schematic illustration of the mechanism for the excitation of kink oscillations of coronal loops, observed 
            in the majority of the studied events. (a) Pre-eruption state of the active region. (b) Displacement of a coronal loop (solid black curve) from 
            its equilibrium state (dashed black line) by an erupting and expanding plasma structure, e.g. a flux rope (grey loop-shaped structure). (c) 
            Oscillatory relaxation of the loop to its equilibrium state after the eruption.</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption"><em>Source: Excitation of kink oscillations of coronal loops: Statistical study, Ivan V. Zimovets. et al. (2015)
            </em> </figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p class="post">
        These oscillations are fundamental modes of coronal loops, with their nodes at the photosphere, i.e. the perturbation at the photosphere is zero. The 
        coronal mass ejections power the kink oscillations.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        There are two different regimes of kink oscillations based on the evolution of their amplitude.
        <ol class="post">
            <li><strong>Decaying-</strong> The oscillations decay in amplitude with time.</li>
            <li><strong>Decayless:</strong> The oscillations do not decay even for a few hours. They have a lower amplitude than the decaying oscillations, and 
                hence they have lower energy.</li>
        </ol>
        Earlier studies predicted that the decayless kink oscillations were powerful enough to power the heating of the Corona. However SDO/AIA observations 
        showed that transverse oscillations in polar plumes have energy flux 4-10 times below than the required.

    <h5>
        The new era of high-resolution imaging: Solar Orbiter/EUI
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        The newly launched Solar Orbiter and EUI are state-of-the-art facilities capable of imaging the solar atmosphere at very high resolutions. The Solar 
        orbiter, at an impressive distance of 0.28 AU from the Sun, can take clear images of the solar atmosphere. Furthermore, unlike any other telescope, it 
        can have a cadence of 2-3 seconds.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        Lastly, it is noteworthy to add that the in-house team comprising Purvi Udhwani, Arpit Shrivastav from ARIES, along with Dr. Ritesh Patel are developing 
        a tool called 'SITCoM: SiRGraF Integrated Tool for Cronal dynaMics', which will aid them in understanding the dynamics of the Solar Corona.
    </p>
</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>arpit</name></author><category term="Coronal heating" /><category term="MHD" /><category term="Solar Orbiter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Coronal heating is a problem that has puzzled scientists for decades. One proposed mechanism for coronal heating is the energy transfer in the solar corona by Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) waves. Several types of MHD waves can be observed in the solar corona, and kink oscillations are a ubiquitous manifestation of largely transverse MHD waves in the solar corona. In this talk, I'll touch upon the historical and introductory aspects of coronal heating, shedding light on the observational perspective. Furthermore, we'll explore the intriguing topic of kink oscillations and their related heating phenomena within the context of the most recent and cutting-edge imaging instruments.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-04-08-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-04-08-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Be Stars: Study of gaseous disc physics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Be-Stars-Study-of-gaseous-disc-physics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be Stars: Study of gaseous disc physics" /><published>2023-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Be-Stars-Study-of-gaseous-disc-physics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Be-Stars-Study-of-gaseous-disc-physics/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post"> 
            Be stars are rapidly rotating massive B type stars surrounded by gaseous equatorial discs and exhibit emission lines of different elements. Study 
            of these emission features produce wealth of information about the disc geometry, kinematics and evolution. However, the disc formation mechanism 
            of Be stars remains unclear till date. I shall highlight the worldwide efforts going on presently to better understand these exotic stars and the 
            physics of their discs. The contribution of the lndian Be star community will also be discussed along with future scope.
        </p>
    </blockquote>

    <h5>
        What are Be stars?
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        First discovered by Father Angello Secchi in 1866. They are massive B-type main sequence stars, which exhibit emission line features, indicating the 
        presence of circumstellar discs which is mostly gas and dust. Be stars are rapid rotators. They have peak incidence at B2 spectral type, and often show 
        high variability in emission lines. The reason it can be concluded that the emission lines are coming from the disc is because photosphere does not 
        yield the same emission lines. Apart from spectroscopic evidence, there is also interferometric evidence.
    </p>

    <h5>
        Why study Be stars?
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ul>
            <li>They are natural laboratories to study stellar disc physics.</li>
            <li>Can used as a probe to study rotation of stars</li>
            <li>The evolutionary status of Be stars is an open issue.</li>
            <li>To better understand the 'Be Phenoenon' - disc formation mechanism</li>
            <li>Their disc show transient nature, which is a less studied area.</li>
            <li>Another interesting but a distant possibility is, by probing these stars we can better understand how to make extreme speed vehicles.</li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        The disc of Be stars is itself a transient, i.e., a disc can appear and vanish within two months.The presence of Balmer line in the emission spectra 
        is a strong evidence pointing towards presence a disc. The other spectral features of Be stars is shown below:
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-03-26-talk/figure1.png" alt="emission-spectra-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1 : Emission spectral features of Be stars</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption"><em>Source: Optical spectroscopy of Galactic field classical Be stars, Banerjee G. et al. (2021)</em></figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>
        Study objectives of Be stars using Indian facilities
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ul>
            <li>To analyze major emission lines present in a large sample of field Be stars</li>
            <li>To study the disc opacity in field Be stars considering the effect of extinction parameter</li>
            <li>To understand the Ca II triplet emission line formation region in Be stars, which is an open question</li>
            <li>To evaluate the disc dissipation and formation timescales of Be stars using multi-epoch optical spectra</li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        Ca II emission line is one the most important features in the study of Be stars. There are two possibilities for the formation of Ca II emission lines. 
        The speaker explored various formation regions of Ca emission lines around the circumstellar disc of Be stars (Banerjee et al. 2021). Their study 
        suggests the possibility that in Be stars, Ca II triplet emission can originate either in
        <ol>
            <li>in the circumbinary disc or,</li>
            <li>from the cooler outer regions of the disc which might not be isothermal in nature. However, 5 out 17 stars were confirmed binaries. Hence, 
                non-thermal disc scenarios seems to be more likely.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>

    <h5>
        Transient nature of Be stars
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        <ul>
            <li>Be stars usually exhibit variability in spectral line profiles.</li>
            <li>Extreme case leads to complete disappearance of Ha emission line, which is indicative of a disc-less state in Be stars.</li>
            <li>Different Be star discs show such transient nature.</li>
            <li>Disc formation mechanism in Be stars still poorly understood. Hence, no clear idea about disc formation and dissipation timescales.</li>
            <li>However, disc loss and reappearing phases of Be stars can be identified by studying their
                Hα line profiles on a regular basis.</li>
        </ul>
        Study of these Hα lines can reveal how stable the disc is and when it started forming.
    </p>

    <h5>
        Classification of stars using epoch-wise Hα variation analysis
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        The speaker studied numerous Be stars in HD 23302 and their Hα line variation, and classified the Be stars as following:
        <ul>
            <li><strong>Group I-</strong> stars possessing stable disc during our observation period</li>
            <li><strong>Group II-</strong> stars where disc building happening during the period of observation</li>
            <li><strong>Group III -</strong> stars undergoing disc dissipation</li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-03-26-talk/figure2.png" alt="epoch-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2 : Epoch-wise variation of the Hα EW against MJD as observed for the stars HD 23302. It shows a trend of 
            increasing Hα EW since 18 February 2019 (MJD 58532). This suggests that HD 23302 might be passing through a phase of disc-formation in the current 
            epochs</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption"><em>Source: Study of the transient nature of classical Be stars using multi-epoch optical spectroscopy, 
            Banerjee G. et al. (2022)</em></figcaption>
    </figure>
</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>gourav</name></author><category term="Be Stars" /><category term="Gaseous Disc" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Be stars are rapidly rotating massive B type stars surrounded by gaseous equatorial discs and exhibit emission lines of different elements. Study of these emission features produce wealth of information about the disc geometry, kinematics and evolution. However, the disc formation mechanism of Be stars remains unclear till date. I shall highlight the worldwide efforts going on presently to better understand these exotic stars and the physics of their discs. The contribution of the lndian Be star community will also be discussed along with future scope.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-03-26-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-03-26-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Curious Straight Ray</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/The-Curious-Straight-Ray/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Curious Straight Ray" /><published>2023-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/The-Curious-Straight-Ray</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/The-Curious-Straight-Ray/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post">
            Astrophysical jets are fascinating phenomena that have been observed in a wide range of astrophysical objects like active galactic nuclei (AGNs), 
            microquasars, neutron stars, young stellar objects (YSOs), and gamma-ray bursts (GRBs). They are narrow, highly collimated outflows of plasma 
            that can extend over vast distances from the central object. Despite years of research and advances in observation and simulation of these objects, 
            the formation, collimation, and composition of these jets still remain as open questions. In this talk, I will give an overview about our 
            understanding of these enigmatic and fascinating objects.
        </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p class="post">
        In 1918, while studying the spiral galaxy NGC 4569, Curtis noticed a straight ray of light extending from the galaxy's nucleus. This ray appeared 
        much brighter than the rest of the galaxy and extended outwards for a considerable distance. The ray was so unusual that Curtis initially thought it 
        might be a comet or some other type of celestial object. After observing the Curious Ray, the astronomer spent several months trying to determine its 
        nature and origin. He examined other galaxies to see if they also had similar rays but found that the NGC 4569 was the only galaxy with such a 
        phenomenon. Curtis also ruled out the possibility that the ray was a reflection of light from a nearby star or planet. Curtis concluded that the 
        Curious Straight Ray was caused by a jet of material ejected from the galaxy's nucleus. This jet was likely the result of a massive explosion, such as 
        a supernova or a quasar. However, at the time of Curtis's discovery, the concept of a quasar was unknown, so he referred to the phenomenon as a "jet." 
        Since Curtis's discovery, astronomers have studied the Curious Straight Ray extensively. We now know that these rays are caused by jets of material 
        being ejected from the nuclei of galaxies. These jets are produced by supermassive black holes at the centre of galaxies, which emit powerful 
        streams of energy as they consume matter.
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-03-18-talk/figure1.png" alt="Relativistic-jets-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1 : Relativistic jets from the nucleus of different astronomical bodies</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption"><em>Source: Mirabel, 2013</em> </figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p class="post">
        Observations of relativistic jets using <em>Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI)</em> techniques have revealed apparent superluminal motion of the 
        jet material. This effect is known as Apparent Faster- Than-Light (AFTL) motion and occurs when the jet is moving at a very high fraction of the speed 
        of light and is pointed close to the observer's line of sight. Superluminal motion refers to the apparent motion of an object at speeds faster than 
        the speed of light. This phenomenon is observed in radio jets emanating from certain active galactic nuclei, where the apparent motion of the jet 
        material can exceed the speed of light. However, this does not violate the laws of physics, as it is a purely observational effect caused by the 
        orientation of the jet relative to the observer.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        The study of superluminal motion in relativistic jets has provided valuable insights into the physics of these objects, including the structure and 
        dynamics of the jet material, the properties of the magnetic fields that accelerate and confine the plasma, and the nature of the accretion 
        processes that power the jets.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        There are two types of Radio Galaxies, based on the relativistic jet it emits from their nucleus, <em>Fanaroff- Riley I(FRI)</em> and 
        <em>Fanaroff- Riley II(FRII)</em>. FRI type galaxies are brighter towards the centre and have two-sided, lower-powered (< ~10<sup>42</sup> erg/s) jets. 
        Plumes are observed in this kind of galaxy. On the other hand, FRII galaxies have one-sided higher-powered (>~10<sup>42</sup> erg/s) jets. FRII 
        galaxies have Hot Spots and Lobes, and their edges are brightened.
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-03-18-talk/figure2.jpg" alt="FRI-&-FRII-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2 : Different types of Radio Galaxies: FRI & FRII</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption"><em>Source: Creston, 2018</em> </figcaption>
    </figure>


</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>raj</name></author><category term="Relativistic Jets" /><category term="Radio Galaxies" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Astrophysical jets are fascinating phenomena that have been observed in a wide range of astrophysical objects like active galactic nuclei (AGNs), microquasars, neutron stars, young stellar objects (YSOs), and gamma-ray bursts (GRBs). They are narrow, highly collimated outflows of plasma that can extend over vast distances from the central object. Despite years of research and advances in observation and simulation of these objects, the formation, collimation, and composition of these jets still remain as open questions. In this talk, I will give an overview about our understanding of these enigmatic and fascinating objects.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-03-18-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-03-18-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fantastic Instruments and How to understand them!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Fantastic-instruments/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fantastic Instruments and How to understand them!" /><published>2023-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Fantastic-instruments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Fantastic-instruments/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post">
            Instruments are the hidden figures of every world, especially astronomy and we need to give them the attention they deserve! In this talk I will 
            attempt to cover the basics of instruments, both ground and space based, used in astronomy all over the world and how they give us the data we use 
            for our research.
        </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p class="post">
        Aberration is a property of optical systems that results in light being spread out over some region of space rather than focussing on a point. The 
        earth's atmosphere aberrates the wavefronts of the EM waves. Due to this aberration, the images of astronomical objects become distorted. To deal with 
        distortions, and to get high-resolution spectra, different kinds of instruments are used in the field of astronomy. Let us look into some of them in 
        today's talk.
    </p>

    <h5>
       MUSE: 
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        MUSE is an Integral Field Spectrograph working in an optical band. It splits the field of view into 24 image segments of 2.5" each. These segments are 
        further sliced into 48 mini slices. Each set of 48 mini slits is fed into one of the spectrographs to produce a set of spectra.
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-03-10-talk/figure1.jpg" alt="FOV-MUSE-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1 : Splitting of the field of view by MUSE</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Source: ESO</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>
        History of microwave astronomy:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        It started with the unintentional discovery of <em>Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB)</em> . Wilson and Penzias were trying to make a microwave antenna 
        for Bell labs. However, they detected a leftover microwave signal coming from all directions of the sky, which was nothing but the CMB.    
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-03-10-talk/figure2.webp" alt="CMB-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2 : Different generations of instruments to search for CMB</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Source: quantuse.com: Cosmic microwave background - The light from the past</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <h5>
        Instruments to detect CMB:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        The first space-based CMB mission was <em>COBE (Cosmic Background Explorer)</em> satellite. It gave the first full-sky map of CMB, which confirmed Big 
        Bang theory predictions. Nasa launched the <em>Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP)</em> in 2001, which revealed that the universe's first stars 
        started shining about 200 million years after the Big Bang. The ESA's Plank space telescope was the latest on the list. CMB measurement needs that 
        noise to be minimal. So, the Planck satellite had an inbuilt system to keep itself cool, and it was sent at the cold L2 point. It had two scientific
        instruments: the <em>High-Frequency Instrument (HFI)</em> and the <em>Low-Frequency Instrument (LFI)</em>.
    </p>

    <h5>
        HIRES:
    </h5>
    <p class="post">
        The <em>High-Resolution Echelle Spectrometer</em> at the Keck's Observatory, Hawai, works in the optical band of em spectra. It has three arms, R, G 
        and B. It helps to break up the incoming light into its different colours to measure the intensity of each colour precisely.
    </p>


    <h5>
        Adaptive Optics:
    </h5>

    <p class="post">
        Take the case of an incoming ray of light coming through the atmosphere. Water droplets distort the wavefronts of the waves in the atmosphere, which 
        work as air lenses. So, the wavefront captured by the instrument is aberrated and tilted. Tip-tilt correction is done on the wavefront to account 
        for the tilt. A deformable mirror is used to account for the aberration. It takes the complementary shape of the wavefront using control electronics 
        so that the actual wavefront can be obtained as output.
        <ul class="post">
            <li>
                In the case of <em>Single Conjugate Adaptive Optics (SCAO)</em>, one guide star (should be present in the same sky patch where we are taking 
                the observation) is used to get the measurement of the wavefront phase, assuming that both the objects face the same amount of aberration.
            </li>
            <li>In the case of <em>Laser Tomography Adaptive Optics (LTAO)</em>, laser beacons are used in the field of view to work as guide stars.</li>
            <li>
                <em>Ground Layer Adaptive Optics (GLAO)</em> is a technique in which several wavefront sensors control one deformable mirror. The guide sources are 
                distributed in a large field of view.
            </li>
            <li>
                <em>Multi Conjugate Adaptive Optics (MCAO)</em> uses multiple guide stars, including natural and Laser stars, several wavefront sensors, and 
                many deformable mirrors.
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>
</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>purvi</name></author><category term="Telescopes" /><category term="MUSE" /><category term="HIRES" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Instruments are the hidden figures of every world, especially astronomy and we need to give them the attention they deserve! In this talk I will attempt to cover the basics of instruments, both ground and space based, used in astronomy all over the world and how they give us the data we use for our research.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-03-10-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-03-10-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the power of Machine Learning and Big Data in Astrophysics with a Test case</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Machine-learning-and-big-data/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the power of Machine Learning and Big Data in Astrophysics with a Test case" /><published>2023-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Machine-learning-and-big-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Machine-learning-and-big-data/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
   <blockquote>
        <p class="post">
            There has been a massive growth in the availability of Astrophysical data in recent years. This growth is going to increase in the future with the 
            advent of newer telescopes like the Square Kilometre Array, the Large Synoptic Survey Telescope now known as the Vera Rubin Telescope, and the 
            Dark energy survey Instrument DESI. This, combined with the existing telescopes, provides a plethora of opportunities to employ ML to solve 
            astrophysical problems. In this talk, I introduce ML in astrophysics and discuss a test case of classifying variable stars using the K nearest 
            neighbor technique in anticipation that the talk will encourage peers to explore astrophysical data sets and appreciate the power and nuances 
            related to algorithms and big data in astrophysics.
        </p>
   </blockquote>

   <p class="post">
        In this talk, we are taken through the journey of basic Machine Learning algorithms and their application towards analysing the enormous chunks of 
        data generated in Astrophysical observations. The speaker also demonstrates the same with a test case he worked on during his Master's project.
   </p>

   <p class="post">
        Times are changing, and gone are the days when we used to think that 1 GB of data was huge. Today, astronomical observations yield Peta-bytes of Data! 
        Earlier, the data was manageable as per human limitations. However, going forward, analysis of big data cannot be achieved using our trivial ways. This 
        is so because there are a limited number of scientists, astronomers, and analysts, but there is no limit to the data we generate daily. The data will 
        keep piling up, and one day we might even run out of storage space.
   </p>

   <p class="post">
        How to tackle this problem? Citizen Science comes to the rescue. We increase the number of people by training the common people (who may not be 
        specialised in Astronomy and Astrophysicists), called Citizen Scientists. One great example of this is the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite 
        (TESS), where Citizen Scientists are trained to label the light curves of the transiting exoplanet. If there is a dip in the light curve, it can be 
        considered an exoplanet. Depending on the dip's period, width, and duration, the exoplanets are further matched with a template to classify the type 
        of exoplanet. The authorship is also shared with the citizen. In Pune, India, we also have such a program named the Pune Knowledge Cluster (PKC), which
        IUCAA and other institutes in Pune operate. They label and categorise the galaxies.
   </p>

   <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-03-03-talk/figure1.png" alt="planet-hunter-TESS-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1 : The TESS Citizen Science program for classifying exoplanets</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Source: Planet Hunters archive</figcaption>
   </figure>

   <p class="post">
        Furthermore, to facilitate these initiatives and make the process faster and more efficient, we finally apply Machine Learning (ML) techniques. 
        Classifying our data using ML has a few basic steps, as follows:
        <ol class="post">
            <li>Importing the Data</li>
            <li>Organise and Preprocess the data- The data should be uniform, i.e., the sampling rate, resolution, and processing should be similar.</li>
            <li>Explore Data and Engineer the features - The features that distinguish one type from the other.</li>
            <li>Build a model - The model should be able to take into account all the features and summarise it so that we can distinguish different 
                types/classes of objects.</li>
            <li>Evaluate the model - The precision of the data is verified using a confusion chart.</li>
            <li>Finally, deploy the model for use.</li>
        </ol>
   </p>

   <p class="post">
        For example, if we want our model to recognise the difference between the letters' J' and 'M', we must first consider how our mind differentiates 
        between the two. We can evaluate the X and Y-axis of the stroke and the time for each stroke. 'J' has a single minima, whereas 'M' has three minimas 
        with an oscillation pattern. On the other hand, 'J' is written quicker than 'M'. Now that we have our features and model, we must test its accuracy 
        using Confusion Charts. In this chart, we draw a matrix comparing the expected vs. the predicted outcomes. If the desired outcome is achieved, we 
        deploy the model to the end user; otherwise, the model is further modified to correct the confusion chart results. It is somewhat like how a child 
        learns to recognise the number '10'. The speaker demonstrates that, in his attempt to classify the letters 'J', 'M', and 'V' using three features, he 
        got an accuracy of 80% and a misclassification of 20%. If the number of features increases, the accuracy also increases. For more features, we need 
        more data.
   </p>

   <p class="post">
        The speaker used a similar kind of approach to classify about 100,000 variable stars. Using features such as the light curve analysis, HR Diagram, 
        Blazkho effect (change of amplitude in different cycles with the same period), binary light curve, distance, entropy (the scatter of the distribution 
        in magnitude) etc., he could classify different variable stars as Cepheids, RR Lyrae, Delta-Scuti and others.
   </p>

   <p class="post">
        We can simplify ML as a mathematical function. The complete system of input and output of that function, including all the other hidden layers, is 
        called a Neural Network. It is named so since it mimics the neurons of the brain. We give different weightage to different features depending upon 
        their importance to classify an object type, and the sum total threshold decides the object's class.
   </p>

   <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-03-03-talk/figure2.png" alt="nueral-network-image">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2 : A simple neural network</figcaption>
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Source: Wikipedia</figcaption>
   </figure>

   <p class="post">
        To summarise, in these modern times, Big Data is inevitable, and ML is a necessary boon to tackle the same. Astrophysics is one such field that must 
        take complete advantage of various ML techniques. The best part of ML is that a combination of some random features yields fruitful results, and we do 
        not know why. This also gives us a deeper insight into how things work in the Universe. ML techniques are fast and efficient, and they can analyse 
        astronomical observations with a speed of thousands of observations per second (or even more). ML is the way to the future for Astrophysical studies.
   </p>
</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>neel</name></author><category term="Machine Learning" /><category term="Nueral Network" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There has been a massive growth in the availability of Astrophysical data in recent years. This growth is going to increase in the future with the advent of newer telescopes like the Square Kilometre Array, the Large Synoptic Survey Telescope now known as the Vera Rubin Telescope, and the Dark energy survey Instrument DESI. This, combined with the existing telescopes, provides a plethora of opportunities to employ ML to solve astrophysical problems. In this talk, I introduce ML in astrophysics and discuss a test case of classifying variable stars using the K nearest neighbor technique in anticipation that the talk will encourage peers to explore astrophysical data sets and appreciate the power and nuances related to algorithms and big data in astrophysics.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-03-03-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-03-03-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gamma Ray Bursts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Gamma-ray-bursts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gamma Ray Bursts" /><published>2023-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Gamma-ray-bursts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Gamma-ray-bursts/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post">
            Gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) are one of the most energetic and luminous events in the universe. These powerful explosions can last from milliseconds to 
            minutes, and they can be hundreds of times brighter than a typical supernova and a million trillion times brighter than the Sun. Despite their 
            discovery decades ago, we still do not fully understand the origins and causes of GRBs. One of the main challenges in studying GRBs is their 
            classification. To unravel this mystery, various classification schemes have been proposed based on different characteristics of the bursts, such 
            as duration, hardness, and spectral properties. Join me as we delve into this problem and explore the latest advancements in solving it.
        </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p class="post">
        The talk started with what GRBs are, how we detect them, and why these areas of astrophysics are full of excitement. GRB is the Burst of gamma rays. 
        “Burst” means a sudden release of emission that lasts from milliseconds to thousands of seconds, and the term gamma is related to the energy of bursts 
        ranging from 100 KeV to 1 MeV. GRBs are the most luminous event since the BIG Bang. Typically &#947-ray luminosity is ~10<sup>51</sup> - 
        10<sup>53</sup>  erg s<sup>-1</sup>. This is more than the total energy the Sun releases in its entire lifetime. We can also compare the luminosity of 
        other objects in the Universe. For example, the luminosity of the Sun is ~10 <sup>33</sup>  erg s <sup>-1</sup> , and the total star-light luminosity 
        of the Milky Way Galaxy is ~10 <sup>44</sup>erg s <sup>-1</sup>. Even the most energetic Active Galactic Nuclei (AGNs) powered by accreting super-massive black holes only 
        have a luminosity of ~10 <sup>48</sup>  erg s <sup>-1</sup>.
    </p>
    
    <h5 class="post">How was it Discovered - It was an accident!</h5>
    <p class="post">
        In 1945, Hiroshima and Nagasaki of Japan were severely destroyed by atomic bombs released by the United States. After this event, nuclear tests were 
        banned all over World. United States launched a series of satellites to monitor compliance with the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty signed by the United 
        States. The discovery of the first GRBs was made in the late 1960s by the military satellite system Vela. Since nuclear energy lies in the gamma 
        frequency range, they discovered some intense flashes, which was a mystery for a long time. Later, from redshift, they concluded that it was 
        extragalactic.
    </p>

    <h5 class="post"> Types of GRBs</h5>
    <p class="post">
        Based on T90 (the duration during which the triggering detector detects 5 % to 95 % of the total fluence), there are two types of GRB.
        <ul class="post">
            <li>Short GRB (T90 < 2 sec) </li>
            <li>Long GRB (T90 > 2 sec)</li>
        </ul>
        Long GRBs are believed to be associated with the death of some special massive star (Supernova and kilonova). In contrast, short GRBs are associated 
        with the merger of compact objects such as Neutron Star-Neutron Star or Neutron Star-Black Hole merger.
    </p>

    <h5 class="post">Why do we need other ways to classify GRB ?</h5>
    <p class="post">
        Since the definition of T90 depends on the energy band and sensitivity of the detector. The same burst may have a longer T90 if the detector is more 
        sensitive or has a softer energy band. Also, the background fluctuations play the villain.
    </p>

    <h5 class="post">What are the other ways ?</h5>
    <p class="post">
        There are two phases in which we observe GRB - one being the Prompt Emission Phase and another being the Afterglow Phase.
    </p>
    <p class="post">
        To point out, we can classify GRBs using the following features:
        <ul class="post">
            <li>Hardness Ratio</li>
            <li>Minimum Variability time scale</li>
            <li>Spectral Lag</li>
            <li>Position in Amati Plane</li>
            <li>Host Properties</li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <h5 class="post">How do we come to know when a GRB takes place? How to detect them?</h5>
    <p class="post">
        We use the Gamma-Ray Coordinate Network, which uses a network of various space-based telescopes such as Fermi and Swift. This network notifies us 
        whenever such a phenomenon takes place. Once notified, we point our optical telescopes in the appropriate direction.
    </p>
    
    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-24-talk/figure1.jpg" alt="GCN Network">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1: The GCN Network used to detect GRBs</figcaption>
    </figure>

</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>dimple</name></author><category term="GRB" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) are one of the most energetic and luminous events in the universe. These powerful explosions can last from milliseconds to minutes, and they can be hundreds of times brighter than a typical supernova and a million trillion times brighter than the Sun. Despite their discovery decades ago, we still do not fully understand the origins and causes of GRBs. One of the main challenges in studying GRBs is their classification. To unravel this mystery, various classification schemes have been proposed based on different characteristics of the bursts, such as duration, hardness, and spectral properties. Join me as we delve into this problem and explore the latest advancements in solving it.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-24-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-24-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mathematical Aspects and Caveats of Temporal Analysis of Light curve</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Mathematical-Aspects-and-Caveats-of-Temporal-Analysis-of-Lightcurve/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mathematical Aspects and Caveats of Temporal Analysis of Light curve" /><published>2023-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Mathematical-Aspects-and-Caveats-of-Temporal-Analysis-of-Lightcurve</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Mathematical-Aspects-and-Caveats-of-Temporal-Analysis-of-Lightcurve/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
    <script src="https://polyfill.io/v3/polyfill.min.js?features=es6"></script>
    <script id="MathJax-script" async src="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/mathjax@3/es5/tex-mml-chtml.js"></script>
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post">
            In the talk, I will briefly start with different behaviors that may appear in and the different samplings of the lightcurves along with the issue 
            to be wary of, while flux to magnitude conversion. The talk will be mainly oriented to periodic search in the lightcurve. The two types of Fourier 
            transforms along with the utility of one over the other will be discussed. I will present some real lightcurves, their temporal analyses that are 
            directly implicated to the topics covered and discuss various properties of a periodogram with the dependence of their peak significance onto 
            their normalizations. A brief disclosure of convolution and its versatility over binning will be discussed as well and if time permits I will also 
            go over Wavelet analysis and its superiority over periodograms.
        </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p class="post">
        This talk will mainly focus on the mathematical aspects of various techniques used to analyze the light curve of the observed data. Light curves are 
        plots showing the variation in brightness or flux of an object over time. This is an essential tool in observational astronomy.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        There are mainly two types of sampling of lightcurve, even and uneven. Mixtures of even and uneven samplings (irrespective of the analysis) should be 
        such that our analysis handles both types of samplings. Any periodic variation may not persist for long due to highly unpredictable behaviour.
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-17-talk/figure1.jpg" alt="Lightcurve sampling">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1: Light curve sampling showing high fluctuations in data</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p class="post">
        Furthermore, we use Periodograms to determine the periodicity of an object from the light curve. The periodogram is represented by:
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        $$P(\omega) \equiv B.\left[(\psi_1(\omega))^2 + (\psi_2(\omega))^2 \right]  $$
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        &#936<sub>1</sub>(&#937) and &#936 <sub>2</sub>(&#937) are real and imaginary parts of the Fourier transform of any time-varying function, where &#937 
        is the frequency.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        Here, "B" is quite important, as it is one of the roots to form periodogram statistics like individual peak significance and global FAP levels. We can 
        also consider it as a normalization constant for statistical balance. Periodograms also solve the problem of discreteness of our usual Fourier 
        transform method. However, we have an additional issue of even and uneven sampling! This is solved using the Lomb Scargle Periodogram (LSP), where the 
        periodogram is written in sine and cosine terms. The Lomb-Scargle periodogram is a well-known algorithm for detecting and characterizing periodic 
        signals in unevenly-sampled data. If the Relative change in frequency is constant, they appear equidistant in log space. Hence, it is better for 
        harmonic search because they will be evenly separated.
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-17-talk/figure2.jpg" alt="LS Periodogram">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2: LS Periodogram</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p class="post">
        Furthermore, the talk continues by discussing the technique of <em>Convolution</em>. Convolution amounts to sliding one function past the other, 
        integrating at each step. Such an operation is commonly used in smoothing a function. It is more versatile than binning (taking average), and binning 
        is a particular case of smoothing through convolution.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        $$ (f * g)(t) \approx \int_{-\infty}^{\infty} f(\tau)g(t-\tau) d\tau $$
    </p>

    <p class="post">  
        <ul class="post">
            <li>If g(x) = Probability Distribution Function such that &#8747 g(x).dx = 1, then convolution becomes a moving average with the desired PDF.</li>
            <li>If g(x) is a rectangular wave function with length N and height 1/N, then the convolution becomes averaging over N data points with equal 
                weightage.</li>
            <li>With proper arbitrary g(x), small, medium and large variations or even flares could be smoothed.</li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        Mathematically, the fact of the invertibility of the convolution mapping (one-to-one) implies that the information content of the convolution is 
        identical to the information content of the original image. Convolution decreases the white noise and does not affect the low-frequency region but the 
        high-frequency region because fluctuations are observed in high-frequency regions. At the same time, the binning (onto, not one-to-one) contains less 
        information and reduces power.
    </p>

    <p class="post">
        If we combine LSP and Convolution properties, we get some additional benefits, for example, if there are any gaps in our observed data, then LSP 
        combined convolution takes care of it.
    </p>

    <figure class="image">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-17-talk/figure3.jpg" alt="periodogram">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 3: Periodograms of Original vs. Convolution vs. Binning</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p class="post">
        <ul class="post">
            A few take-home points from the talk:
            <li>There happens to be a true hidden power spectrum over which the periodogram is distributed in a chi-square fashion with two degrees of 
                freedom.</li>
            <li>The noise reduction in the high-frequency regime before the Nyquist frequency is still unexplored.</li>
            <li>The Lomb-Scargle Periodogram cannot tell the time of inset or disappearance of any significant peak.</li>
            <li>The Lomb-Scargle Periodogram cannot assess the time evolution of an already existing significant peak.</li>
            <li>The Wavelet analysis is capable of handling the last two inefficacy of LSP.</li>
        </ul>
    </p>

</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>shubham</name></author><category term="Blazar" /><category term="Time Series Analysis" /><category term="LombScargle Periodogram" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the talk, I will briefly start with different behaviors that may appear in and the different samplings of the lightcurves along with the issue to be wary of, while flux to magnitude conversion. The talk will be mainly oriented to periodic search in the lightcurve. The two types of Fourier transforms along with the utility of one over the other will be discussed. I will present some real lightcurves, their temporal analyses that are directly implicated to the topics covered and discuss various properties of a periodogram with the dependence of their peak significance onto their normalizations. A brief disclosure of convolution and its versatility over binning will be discussed as well and if time permits I will also go over Wavelet analysis and its superiority over periodograms.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-17-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-17-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Active Galaxies: Most Powerful Objects in the Universe – An Overview</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Active-Galaxies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Active Galaxies: Most Powerful Objects in the Universe – An Overview" /><published>2023-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Active-Galaxies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Active-Galaxies/"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/custom.css">
</head>
<body>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="post"> Active galaxies are highly luminous astrophysical sources in the universe powered by “supermassive black holes” via processes known 
            as “accretion”. They contain a highly bright, compact region at the galaxy’s center called “active galactic nuclei” (AGN). Their emission spreads 
            over a wide range of frequencies through radio to γ-rays. Both thermal and non-thermal radiations from different components of AGN contribute to 
            the total observed emission. They exhibit extreme variations ranging from all the time-scale from minutes to years across the electromagnetic band.
            These variations occur as flares or quiescent/low-activity states. Studying the cause for such physical properties of AGNs through multi-frequency 
            data using ground and space-based observatories has been found to be one of the most effective ways in the past. Despite such studies in various 
            wavebands, there are several questions for which answers are not fully understood. In this talk, the speaker will briefly introduce AGN and its 
            current understanding status, along with the scope of AGN research.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <p class="post">We present to you the second talk of our ARIES Science Club by Dr. Krishna Mohana. On our Earth, the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) generates 
        particles with energies in the Tera electron volts (TeV) range, which is a lot! However, there are some mysterious and powerful objects in our Universe
        where this energy is just child's play. They are called AGN (Active Galactic Nuclei).
    </p>

    <p class="post">An AGN is a small region at the center of some galaxies that is far brighter than can be explained by the stellar population alone. AGNs 
        emit radiation from radio waves to gamma rays across the entire electromagnetic spectrum. Carl Seyfert discovered this incredible phenomenon in 1943. 
        The galaxies which contain these AGNs were thus named Seyfert Galaxies.
    </p>

    <figure>
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/figure1.jpg" alt="Unified model of AGN">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 1: Unified model of AGN</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p>The AGN structure has certain key components:
        <ul class="post">
            <li>The central engine (supermassive black hole mass ~10<sup>8</sup> - 10<sup>9</sup> M<sub>&#9737</sub>)</li>
            <li>Accretion disk</li>
            <li>Corona</li>
            <li>Broad line region</li>
            <li>Narrow line region</li>
            <li>Dusty torus</li>
            <li>Relativistic jets</li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <p class="post">Further, AGNs are classified in terms of the observer's viewing angle, the energy of the jets, and the width of the emission line. The 
        picture below depicts the various classifications:
    </p>

    <figure style="text-align: center;">
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/figure2.jpg" alt="classifications of AGN">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 2: Classifications of AGNs</figcaption>
    </figure>

    <p class="post">Another interesting consequence of AGN jets is Superluminal motion, which occurs when an emission region moves at a velocity close to the 
        speed of light along a direction that forms a small angle with the observer's line of sight. The time interval between the emission of two successive 
        photons, as measured in the observer's frame, is reduced & the source appears to move faster than its actual velocity.
    </p>

    <p class="post">Interestingly, in 1959, a star-like object was discovered in radio band. An optical starlight source was observed in the same region with 
        unusual properties, such as emission lines. These were termed quasi-stellar radio sources (in short, Quasars) because the nature of these objects is 
        entirely unknown. It is hard to prepare a short and appropriate nomenclature for them so that their essential properties are obvious from their name.
        Quasars, also a type of AGN, are the most luminous objects in our Universe, powered by supermassive black holes which are a billion times more massive
        than our Sun.
    </p>

    <p class="post">We can detect AGNs through multi-messenger astronomy (gamma-rays through radio waves, jets) and polarization. Polarization observation of 
        AGN jets provides valuableinformation about their magnetic field. Due to the magnetic field's twisting, we can observe the frame-dragging effect of a 
        spinning black hole and the differential rotation of the accretion disk
    </p>

    <p class="post">A few ground and space observatories to detect the AGN mechanisms are: EGRET(Energetic Gamma Ray Experiment Telescope), FGST (Fermi 
        Gamma-ray Space Telescope), SWIFT, India's AstroSAT, our ARIES's very own DOT 3.6m (Devesthal Optical Telescope). 
    </p>

    <p class="post">Through studying AGN, we can enhance our understanding of the origin of jets, emission mechanism, accretion disk, supermassive blackhole, 
        extragalactic sources, and early Universe, and hence, test the general theory of relativity.
    </p>

    <p class="post">Some of the numerous open questions in this field?
        <ul class="post">
            <li>Where along the jet, do the high-energy and very high-energy y-ray emissions
                predominantly originate?
            </li>
            <li>Whether the high energy emission mechanism is leptonic, hadronic, or mixed?
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>

    <figure>
        <img src="/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/figure3.png" alt="krishna explaining">
        <figcaption class="post-caption">Figure 3: Dr. Krishna explaining the radiative processes involved in the jet emissions</figcaption>
    </figure>

</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>krishna</name></author><category term="AGN" /><category term="Relativistic Jets" /><category term="Accretion Disk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Active galaxies are highly luminous astrophysical sources in the universe powered by “supermassive black holes” via processes known as “accretion”. They contain a highly bright, compact region at the galaxy’s center called “active galactic nuclei” (AGN). Their emission spreads over a wide range of frequencies through radio to γ-rays. Both thermal and non-thermal radiations from different components of AGN contribute to the total observed emission. They exhibit extreme variations ranging from all the time-scale from minutes to years across the electromagnetic band. These variations occur as flares or quiescent/low-activity states. Studying the cause for such physical properties of AGNs through multi-frequency data using ground and space-based observatories has been found to be one of the most effective ways in the past. Despite such studies in various wavebands, there are several questions for which answers are not fully understood. In this talk, the speaker will briefly introduce AGN and its current understanding status, along with the scope of AGN research.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/cover-pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2023-02-10-talk/cover-pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>